Harry Sinclair Drago Papers
Harry Sinclair Drago Papers
1926-1968
Drago, Harry Sinclair, 1888-1979.
15.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American novelist and short story writer who specialized in historical fiction set in the Southwestern States. Collection includes correspondence (1925-1967); typescript books and stories; and published material by and about Drago.
148951
Biographical History
American novelist Harry Sinclair Drago (1888-1979 or 1980) was born in White Plains, New York. He held a number of jobs in the writing and publishing industry, including reporter and columnist for the Toledo Bee in Toledo, Ohio and Hollywood scriptwriter (1928-1933), but is best known for his historical fiction, most of which was set in the American Southwest. His novels include Oh Suzanna, Whispering Sage, Out of the Silent North, Buckskin Affair, Fenced Off, and Decision at Broken Butte.
Drago was a prolific writer, averaging three books a year, and published more than a hundred books over his career. In addition to his novels, he contributed articles and short stories to The Westerners and other publications and wrote several screenplays and novelizations; in his later years he turned his hand from historical fiction to non-fiction histories of the American West. He also wrote under several pseudonyms: Sinclair Drago, Grant Sinclair, Stewart Cross, Kirk Deming, Will Ermine, Peter Field, Bliss Lomax, and J. Wesley Putnam.
Drago was a member of the Publication Committee of the Westerners, New York Posse (branch), a non-profit educational organization of those whose interest is to preserve and record the cultural background and development of the West. His work received many awards, among them the Buffalo Award for best western book of the year (1960) for Wild, Woolly, and Wicked, the National Cowboy Hall of Fame Award (1970) for The Great Range Wars, and the Western Heritage Award (1971).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harry Sinclair Drago Papers consists of two accessions which have not been integrated. The collection includes correspondence, writings, photographs, manuscripts, and published material.
Manuscripts contains handwritten and typed manuscripts of articles, books, short stories and plays, both by Drago and others, as well as those sets of gallery proofs. Published material contains newspaper clippings about others, articles by Drago and others, one novelette, and one periodical.
The 1969 additions consist of biographical and background material, correspondence, writings and photographs. Biographical and background material (1969 additions) contains a brief printed autobiography, newspaper clippings about Western subjects, and personal ephemera.
Correspondence (1969 additions) contains incoming and a few outgoing letters. Most concerns Drago's writing, though there are a few personal in nature. Box 1 includes a selected index to correspondence with specific dates of letters; a summary of this with inclusive dates is reproduced at the end of this finding aid.
Writings (1969 additions), most undated, includes manuscripts, reviews of his books, and notes. Photographs (1969 additions) contains miscellaneous photos (Tom Mix, others).
Arrangement of the Collection
Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically first by type, then by author, and then by title. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type and then by author if applicable. Personal correspondence is arranged chronologically; business correspondence is arranged alphabetically (as received). Writings in the 1969 additions are arranged alphabetically by type and then by title.
Note that box numbers are not unique. Please specify accession and box number and title when requesting material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Drago, Harry Sinclair, 1888-1979, Archives.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Southwestern States, Fiction.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harry S. Drago. Gift of Dodd, Mead & Company Inc.
Inventory
- Manuscripts
  - Articles
    - Barber, James, "The Eyes of the Post Office" (Box 1)
  - Books
    - by Drago
      - Bad Boy (Box 1)
      - Buckskin Affair (Box 1)
      - Buckskin Meadows (Box 1)
      - The Champ (Box 2)
      - Cowtowns of Kansas (Box 2)
      - The Desert Hawk (Box 2)
      - Desert Water (Box 3)
      - Done in the Open (Box 3)
      - Epitaph for a Marshall (Box 3)
      - Fenced Off (Box 3, 4)
      - Good Men and Bad (Box 4)
      - Great American Cattle Trails (Box 4, 5)
      - Gun with a Waiting Notch (Box 5)
      - The Last Patrol (Dead Men's Gold) (Box 5)
      - Lost Bonanzas, 1964 (Box 5)
      - Many Beavers (Box 6)
      - Mesquite (Box 6)
      - Montana Road (Box 6)
      - Nailed Down (Box 6)
      - No Parking (Box 6, 7)
      - Opening at the West (Box 7)
      - Outlaws on Horseback (Box 7, 8)
      - Plundered Range (Box 8)
      - Rebel Basin (Box 8)
      - Red River Valley (Box 8, 9)
      - Spawn of the North (Box 9)
      - The Steamboaters (Box 9)
      - Sun in Their Eyes (Box 10)
      - Sunrise on the Cimarron (Box 10)
      - Wagon Road to Virginia City (Box 10)
      - When the Fish are Rising (Box 11)
      - The Wild Bunch (Box 11)
      - Wild Grass (Box 11, 12)
    - by Drago as Will Ermine
      - Decision at Broken Butte (Box 12)
      - The Driftin' Kid (Box 12)
      - Frenchman's River (Box 13)
      - Laramie Rides Alone (Box 13)
      - Lobo Law (Box 13)
      - Longhorn Empire (Box 13, 14)
      - Pay Off at Black Hawk (Box 14)
      - Rider of the Midnight Range (Box 14)
      - Rustler's Bend (Box 14)
      - The Silver Star (Box 15)
    - by Drago as Bliss Lomax
      - Appointment on the Yellowstone (Box 15)
      - Honky-Tonk Woman (Box 15, 16)
      - Last Call for a Gunfighter (Box 16)
      - The Law Busters (Box 17)
      - Riders of the Buffalo Grass (Box 17)
      - Shadow Mountain (Box 17)
      - Stranger with a Gun (Box 18)
      - Trail Dust (Box 18)
  - Fragments
    - by Drago
      - All American (Box 19)
      - Beyond the Sound of Bugles (Box 19)
      - The Smilin' Kid (Box 19)
    - by Waller, Helen
      - A Girl's Privilege (Box 19)
    - Unidentified, 3 items (Box 19)
  - Galley Proofs
    - by Drago
      - Buckskin Affair (Box 19)
      - Red River Valley (Box 19)
    - by Drago as Will Ermine
      - Longhorn Empire (Box 19)
  - Maps
    - Unidentified (Box 20)
  - Notes
    - by Drago (Box 20)
  - Plays
    - by Drago
      - Cobra Song (with Charleson Gray) (Box 20)
      - King of the Kongo (Box 20)
      - The Lotus Lady (Box 20)
      - Nothing to Wear (with Harry Carlisle), 1928 (Box 20)
    - by Neville, John T.
      - Rolling Thunder, 1928 (Box 20)
  - Short Stories
    - by Drago
      - All the Brothers Were Bad (Box 20)
      - A Man Learns Fast (Box 20)
      - Cowards Don't Come Back (Box 20)
      - Death Rides the River (Box 20)
      - The Drifting Kid Moves On (Box 20)
      - Dusty Saddles (Box 20)
      - Main Event (Box 20)
      - Night Haul (Box 21)
      - Pardners of the Malpais (Box 21)
      - Raw Land (Box 21)
      - Savage Cargo (with Thomas Springer) (Box 21)
      - Six-Gun Justice (Box 21)
      - Sundown (Box 21)
      - Washout at Ute Crossing (Box 21)
      - Watchdog at Lonesome Creek (Box 21)
      - Unidentified, Untitled (Box 21)
  - Story Synopses
    - by Drago
      - Barbed Wire (Box 22)
      - The Cheyenne Trail (Box 22)
      - The Cowboy Kid (Box 22)
      - The Cyclone Lover (Box 22)
      - Drums of India (Box 22)
      - Everything to Win (Box 22)
      - Good Medicine (Box 22)
      - Hello Cheyenne (Box 22)
      - A Horseman of the Plains (Box 22)
      - The Iron Road (Box 22)
      - Ladies Must Pay (Box 22)
      - McCoy Gangster Story (Box 22)
      - On the Spot (Box 22)
      - Painted Post (Box 22)
      - The Pride of Arabia (Box 22)
      - A Romance of the Underworld (Box 22)
      - Six-Gun Ransom (Box 22)
      - Tony Gets His Man (Box 22)
      - Under Western Skies (Box 22)
    - by Redden, Francis J.
      - The Solid Man (Box 22)
    - Unidentified (Box 22)
- Published material
  - Articles
    - by Drago
      - Red River Station, 1961 (Box 1)
      - The Wagon Road to Virginia City, 1962 (Box 1)
    - by Dobie, J. Frank
      - E. Douglas Branch, Singularisimo, 1962 (Box 1)
    - by Traxler, Ralph
      - The Texas & Pacific Railroad Land Grants (Box 1)
    - by Wilson, Glen
      - Old Red River Station (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About others, 1875 (reprinted, 1955); 1926 (Box 1)
  - Novelettes
    - by Drago
      - More Precious than Gold (Box 1)
  - Periodicals
    - Publishers Weekly Vol. 164, no. 14, Oct. 3, 1953
- Biographical and background material (1969 additions)
  - Published material, 1936; 1937,; 1939,; 1942,; 1964,; undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence (1969 additions)
  - Personal
    - 1903-1939, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - 1940-1956, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - Undated (Box 2)
  - Business
    - H. K. Fly Publishing Company, 9 Jan 1919 - 20 Feb 1920 (Box 3)
    - William Morrow and Company, 30 Oct 1933 - 1 May 1951 (Box 3)
    - Mary Leonard Pritchett, 28 Dec 1935 - 9 Sep 1942 (Box 3)
    - Louis H. Silberkleit, 12 Nov 1935 - 13 Apr 1940 (Box 3)
- Writings (1969 additions)
  - Books
    - Great American Cattle Trails, undated; chs 1-10 typescript carbon; chs 11-21 incomplete typescript carbon (Box 3)
    - Farewell Frontier, undated; original typescript revised and typescript carbon revised; incomplete typescript carbon revised; chs 1-6 incomplete original typescript revised (Box 3)
    - Honky Tonk Woman (writing as Bliss Lomax), undated; chs 1-13 original typescript revised (Box 3)
    - Honky Tonk Woman (writing as Bliss Lomax), undated; chs 14-26 original typescript revised; list of characters; original typescript revised (Box 4)
    - Laramie Rides Alone (writing as Will Ermine), undated; original typescript revised (Box 4)
    - The Last Patrol, undated; cits; original typescript revised (Box 4)
    - The Law Busters, undated; typescript carbon; [synopsis] original ts (Box 4)
    - The Match King by Einar Thorvaldson, undated; incomplete original typescript revised (Box 4)
    - Outlaws on Horseback, undated; chs 1-12 typescript carbon revised (Box 4)
    - Outlaws on Horseback, 1965; undated; chs 13-28 typescript carbon revised; published material 6 Jan 1965 (Box 5)
    - Red River Valley book review, 1962-1963; 1968; newspaper clippings; correspondence (Box 5)
    - Roads to Empire, 1968; chs 1-22 printer's copy typescript carbon revised; galleys revised; page proofs; final proofs (Box 5)
    - The Steamboaters, 1967; undated; chs 1-10 printer's copy original typescript revised; chs 11-21 printer's copy original typescript revised; galleys; page proofs, annotated; front matter, bibliography, index printer's copy original typescript revised; correspondence; final proofs, annotated; book reviews (photocopies of newspaper clippings) (Box 6)
    - Trigger Gospel, undated; book review; book cover; published material (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7)
- Photographs (1969 additions)
  - Tom Mix and others, undated (Box 7)
Selected index to correspondence
Following is a summary list with inclusive dates. A detailed index with specific dates is included in Box 1.
Curtis Brown, Ltd. 1939-1956
John Burr 1939-1952, undated
A.L. Burt Company 1929-1934
Century Publications 1922-1949
Doubleday, Doran and Co. 1916-1937
Edward A. Ducker 1935-1940
Farrar and Rinehart, Inc. Publishers 1941-1944
Fox Film Corporation 1926-1927
Robert Thomas Hardy, Inc. 1935, 1940
Marguerite Harper 1952-1955
Franz. J. Horch 1949-1951
Lichtig-Englander 1928-1951, updated
Macaulay Company 1925-1939, undated
Frank A. Munsey Co. 1923-1928
Popular Library 1939-1952
Popular Publications 1937
Short Stories 1925-1942
Smart Set 1926
Street and Smith Publications 1939-1953
H.N. Swanson Inc. 1954-1955
Warner Brothers 1937-1947
Western Printing and Lithographic Company 1947-1954
World Publishing Company 1943-1949